<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Practical Content | Data Analytics</title>
    <link>/example/</link>
      <atom:link href="/example/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Practical Content</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <image>
      <url>/img/social-image.png</url>
      <title>Practical Content</title>
      <link>/example/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Working with R and RStudio</title>
      <link>/example/00-example/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/example/00-example/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;div id=&#34;TOC&#34;&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#introduction-to-examples&#34;&gt;Introduction to Examples&lt;/a&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#getting-started&#34;&gt;Getting started with &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; and RStudio&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-r-console&#34;&gt;The &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; console&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#scripts&#34;&gt;Scripts&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#rstudio&#34;&gt;RStudio&lt;/a&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-panes&#34;&gt;The panes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#key-bindings&#34;&gt;Key bindings&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#running-commands-while-editing-scripts&#34;&gt;Running commands while editing scripts&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#installing-r-packages&#34;&gt;Installing &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; packages&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&#34;introduction-to-examples&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Introduction to Examples&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Examples in this class are designed to be presented in-class. Accordingly, the notes here are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; comprehensive. Instead, they are intended to guide students through&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m also aware that my writing is dry and lifeless. If you’re reading this online without the advantage of seeing it in person, don’t worry—I’ll be “funnier” in class.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;getting-started&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Getting started with &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; and RStudio&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; is not a programming language like &lt;code&gt;C&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;Java&lt;/code&gt;. It was not created by software engineers for software development. Instead, it was developed by statisticians as an interactive environment for data analysis. You can read the full history in the paper A Brief History of S&lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. The interactivity is an indispensable feature in data science because, as you will soon learn, the ability to quickly explore data is a necessity for success in this field. However, like in other programming languages, you can save your work as scripts that can be easily executed at any moment. These scripts serve as a record of the analysis you performed, a key feature that facilitates reproducible work. If you are an expert programmer, you should not expect &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; to follow the conventions you are used—assuming this will leave you disappointed. If you are patient, you will come to appreciate the unequal power of &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; when it comes to data analysis and data visualization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other attractive features of &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; is free and open source&lt;a href=&#34;#fn3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It runs on all major platforms: Windows, Mac OS, UNIX/Linux.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scripts and data objects can be shared seamlessly across platforms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is a large, growing, and active community of &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; users and, as a result, there are numerous resources for learning and asking questions&lt;a href=&#34;#fn4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref4&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;#fn5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref5&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;#fn6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref6&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is easy for others to contribute add-ons which enables developers to share software implementations of new data science methodologies. The latest methods and tools are developed in &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; for a wide variety of disciplines and since social science is so broad, &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; is one of the few tools that spans the varied social sciences.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;the-r-console&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; console&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interactive data analysis usually occurs on the &lt;em&gt;R console&lt;/em&gt; that executes commands as you type them. There are several ways to gain access to an &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; console. One way is to simply start &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; on your computer. The console looks something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/R_console2.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a quick example, try using the console to calculate a 15% tip on a meal that cost $19.71:&lt;a href=&#34;#fn7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref7&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;7&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;0.15 * 19.71  &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## [1] 2.9565&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note that in this course (at least, on most browsers), grey boxes are used to show &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; code typed into the &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; console. The symbol &lt;code&gt;##&lt;/code&gt; is used to denote what the &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; console outputs.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;scripts&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Scripts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the great advantages of &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; over point-and-click analysis software is that you can save your work as scripts. You can edit and save these scripts using a text editor. The material in this course was developed using the interactive &lt;em&gt;integrated development environment&lt;/em&gt; (IDE) RStudio&lt;a href=&#34;#fn8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref8&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;8&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. RStudio includes an editor with many &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; specific features, a console to execute your code, and other useful panes, including one to show figures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/RStudio.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most web-based &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; consoles also provide a pane to edit scripts, but not all permit you to save the scripts for later use. On the upper-right part of this webpage you’ll see a little button with the &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; logo. You can access a web-based console there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;rstudio&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;RStudio&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RStudio will be our launching pad for data science projects. It not only provides an editor for us to create and edit our scripts but also provides many other useful tools. In this section, we go over some of the basics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;the-panes&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The panes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you start RStudio for the first time, you will see three panes. The left pane shows the &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; console. On the right, the top pane includes tabs such as &lt;em&gt;Environment&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;History&lt;/em&gt;, while the bottom pane shows five tabs: &lt;em&gt;File&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Plots&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Packages&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Help&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Viewer&lt;/em&gt; (these tabs may change in new versions). You can click on each tab to move across the different features.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To start a new script, you can click on File, then New File, then &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; Script.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This starts a new pane on the left and it is here where you can start writing your script.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;key-bindings&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Key bindings&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many tasks we perform with the mouse can be achieved with a combination of key strokes instead. These keyboard versions for performing tasks are referred to as &lt;em&gt;key bindings&lt;/em&gt;. For example, we just showed how to use the mouse to start a new script, but you can also use a key binding: Ctrl+Shift+N on Windows and command+shift+N on the Mac.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although in this tutorial we often show how to use the mouse, &lt;strong&gt;we highly recommend that you memorize key bindings for the operations you use most&lt;/strong&gt;. RStudio provides a useful cheat sheet with the most widely used commands. You might want to keep this handy so you can look up key-bindings when you find yourself performing repetitive point-and-clicking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;running-commands-while-editing-scripts&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Running commands while editing scripts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many editors specifically made for coding. These are useful because color and indentation are automatically added to make code more readable. RStudio is one of these editors, and it was specifically developed for R. One of the main advantages provided by RStudio over other editors is that we can test our code easily as we edit our scripts. Below we show an example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s start by opening a new script as we did before. A next step is to give the script a name. We can do this through the editor by saving the current new unnamed script. To do this, click on the save icon or use the key binding Ctrl+S on Windows and command+S on the Mac.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you ask for the document to be saved for the first time, RStudio will prompt you for a name. A good convention is to use a descriptive name, with lower case letters, no spaces, only hyphens to separate words, and then followed by the suffix &lt;em&gt;.R&lt;/em&gt;. We will call this script &lt;em&gt;my-first-script.R&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we are ready to start editing our first script. The first lines of code in an &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; script are dedicated to loading the libraries we will use. Another useful RStudio feature is that once we type &lt;code&gt;library()&lt;/code&gt; it starts auto-completing with libraries that we have installed. Note what happens when we type &lt;code&gt;library(ti)&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another feature you may have noticed is that when you type &lt;code&gt;library(&lt;/code&gt; the second parenthesis is automatically added. This will help you avoid one of the most common errors in coding: forgetting to close a parenthesis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we can continue to write code. As an example, we will make a graph showing murder totals versus population totals by state. Once you are done writing the code needed to make this plot, you can try it out by &lt;em&gt;executing&lt;/em&gt; the code. To do this, click on the &lt;em&gt;Run&lt;/em&gt; button on the upper right side of the editing pane. You can also use the key binding: Ctrl+Shift+Enter on Windows or command+shift+return on the Mac.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you run the code, you will see it appear in the &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; console and, in this case, the generated plot appears in the plots console. Note that the plot console has a useful interface that permits you to click back and forward across different plots, zoom in to the plot, or save the plots as files.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To run one line at a time instead of the entire script, you can use Control-Enter on Windows and command-return on the Mac.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;fyi&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SETUP TIP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Change the option &lt;em&gt;Save workspace to .RData on exit&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;Never&lt;/em&gt; and uncheck the &lt;em&gt;Restore .RData into workspace at start&lt;/em&gt;. By default, when you exit &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; saves all the objects you have created into a file called .RData. This is done so that when you restart the session in the same folder, it will load these objects. I find that this causes confusion especially when sharing code with colleagues or peers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;installing-r-packages&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Installing &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; packages&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The functionality provided by a fresh install of &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; is only a small fraction of what is possible. In fact, we refer to what you get after your first install as &lt;em&gt;base R&lt;/em&gt;. The extra functionality comes from add-ons available from developers. There are currently hundreds of these available from CRAN and many others shared via other repositories such as GitHub. However, because not everybody needs all available functionality, &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; instead makes different components available via &lt;em&gt;packages&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; makes it very easy to install packages from within R. For example, to install the &lt;strong&gt;dslabs&lt;/strong&gt; package, which we use to share datasets and code related to this book, you would type:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;install.packages(&amp;quot;dslabs&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In RStudio, you can navigate to the &lt;em&gt;Tools&lt;/em&gt; tab and select install packages. We can then load the package into our &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; sessions using the &lt;code&gt;library&lt;/code&gt; function:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;library(dslabs)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you go through this book, you will see that we load packages without installing them. This is because once you install a package, it remains installed and only needs to be loaded with &lt;code&gt;library&lt;/code&gt;. The package remains loaded until we quit the &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; session. If you try to load a package and get an error, it probably means you need to
install it first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can install more than one package at once by feeding a character vector to this function:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;install.packages(c(&amp;quot;tidyverse&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;dslabs&amp;quot;))&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One advantage of using RStudio is that it auto-completes package names once you start typing, which is helpful when you do not remember the exact spelling of the package. Once you select your package, we recommend selecting all the defaults. Note that installing &lt;strong&gt;tidyverse&lt;/strong&gt; actually installs several packages. This commonly occurs when a package has &lt;em&gt;dependencies&lt;/em&gt;, or uses functions from other packages. When you load a package using &lt;code&gt;library&lt;/code&gt;, you also load its dependencies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once packages are installed, you can load them into &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; and you do not need to install them again, unless you install a fresh version of R. Remember packages are installed in &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; not RStudio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is helpful to keep a list of all the packages you need for your work in a script because if you need to perform a fresh install of R, you can re-install all your packages by simply running a script.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can see all the packages you have installed using the following function:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;installed.packages()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we move through this course, we will constantly be adding to our toolbox of packages. Accordingly, you will need to keep track to ensure you have the requisite package for any given lecture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Comments from previous classes indicate that I am not, in fact, funny.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://pdfs.semanticscholar.org/9b48/46f192aa37ca122cfabb1ed1b59866d8bfda.pdf&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://pdfs.semanticscholar.org/9b48/46f192aa37ca122cfabb1ed1b59866d8bfda.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn3&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://opensource.org/history&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://opensource.org/history&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn4&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://stats.stackexchange.com/questions/138/free-resources-for-learning-r&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://stats.stackexchange.com/questions/138/free-resources-for-learning-r&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn5&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.r-project.org/help.html&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://www.r-project.org/help.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn6&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://stackoverflow.com/documentation/r/topics&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://stackoverflow.com/documentation/r/topics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn7&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;But probably tip more than 15%. Times are tough, man.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn8&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rstudio.com/&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://www.rstudio.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to Visualization</title>
      <link>/example/01-example/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/example/01-example/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;div id=&#34;TOC&#34;&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#introduction-to-data-visualization&#34;&gt;Introduction to data visualization&lt;/a&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#code&#34;&gt;Code&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&#34;introduction-to-data-visualization&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Introduction to data visualization&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at the numbers and character strings that define a dataset is rarely useful. To convince yourself, print and stare at the US murders data table:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;library(dslabs)
data(murders)
head(murders)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;##        state abb region population total
## 1    Alabama  AL  South    4779736   135
## 2     Alaska  AK   West     710231    19
## 3    Arizona  AZ   West    6392017   232
## 4   Arkansas  AR  South    2915918    93
## 5 California  CA   West   37253956  1257
## 6   Colorado  CO   West    5029196    65&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do you learn from staring at this table? Even though it is a relatively straightforward table, we can’t &lt;strong&gt;learn&lt;/strong&gt; anything. For starters, it is grossly abbreviated, though you could scroll through. In doing so, how quickly might you be able to determine which states have the largest populations? Which states have the smallest? How populous is a typical state? Is there a relationship between population size and total murders? How do murder rates vary across regions of the country? For most folks, it is quite difficult to extract this information just by looking at the numbers. In contrast, the answer to the questions above are readily available from examining this plot:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/example/01-example_files/figure-html/ggplot-example-plot-0-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are reminded of the saying: “A picture is worth a thousand words”. Data visualization provides a powerful way to communicate a data-driven finding. In some cases, the visualization is so convincing that no follow-up analysis is required. You should consider visualization the most potent tool in your data analytics arsenal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The growing availability of informative datasets and software tools has led to increased reliance on data visualizations across many industries, academia, and government. A salient example is news organizations, which are increasingly embracing &lt;em&gt;data journalism&lt;/em&gt; and including effective &lt;em&gt;infographics&lt;/em&gt; as part of their reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A particularly salient example—given the current state of the world—is a Wall Street Journal article&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; showing data related to the impact of vaccines on battling infectious diseases. One of the graphs shows measles cases by US state through the years with a vertical line demonstrating when the vaccine was introduced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/example/01-example_files/figure-html/wsj-vaccines-example-1.png&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Source: &lt;a href=&#34;http://graphics.wsj.com/infectious-diseases-and-vaccines/&#34;&gt;Wall Street Journal&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another striking example comes from a New York Times chart&lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which summarizes scores from the NYC Regents Exams. As described in
the article&lt;a href=&#34;#fn3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, these scores are collected for several reasons, including to determine if a student graduates from high school. In New York City you need a 65 to pass. The distribution of the test scores forces us to notice something somewhat problematic:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/example/01-example_files/figure-html/regents-exams-example-1.png&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Source: &lt;a href=&#34;http://graphics8.nytimes.com/images/2011/02/19/nyregion/19schoolsch/19schoolsch-popup.gif&#34;&gt;New York Times&lt;/a&gt; via Amanda Cox)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most common test score is the minimum passing grade, with very few scores just below the threshold. This unexpected result is consistent with students close to passing having their scores bumped up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an example of how data visualization can lead to discoveries which would otherwise be missed if we simply subjected the data to a battery of data analysis tools or procedures. Data visualization is the strongest tool of what we call &lt;em&gt;exploratory data analysis&lt;/em&gt; (EDA). John W. Tukey&lt;a href=&#34;#fn4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref4&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, considered the father of EDA, once said,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The greatest value of a picture is when it forces us to notice what we never expected to see.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many widely used data analysis tools were initiated by discoveries made via EDA. EDA is perhaps the most important part of data analysis, yet it is one that is often overlooked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Data visualization is also now pervasive in philanthropic and educational organizations. In the talks New Insights on Poverty&lt;a href=&#34;#fn5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref5&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and The Best Stats You’ve Ever Seen&lt;a href=&#34;#fn6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref6&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Hans Rosling forces us to notice the unexpected with a series of plots related to world health and economics. In his videos, he uses animated graphs to show us how the world is changing and how old narratives are no longer true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/example/01-example_files/figure-html/gampnider-example-plot-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is also important to note that mistakes, biases, systematic errors and other unexpected problems often lead to data that should be handled with care. Failure to discover these problems can give rise to flawed analyses and false discoveries. As an example, consider that measurement devices sometimes fail and that most data analysis procedures are not designed to detect these. Yet these data analysis procedures will still give you an answer. The fact that it can be difficult or impossible to notice an error just from the reported results makes data visualization particularly important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, we will learn the basics of data visualization and exploratory data analysis. We will use the &lt;strong&gt;ggplot2&lt;/strong&gt; package to code. To learn the very basics, we will start with a somewhat artificial example: heights reported by students. Then we will cover the two examples mentioned above: 1) world health and economics and 2) infectious disease trends in the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, there is much more to data visualization than what we cover here. The following are references for those who wish to learn more:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ER Tufte (1983) The visual display of quantitative information.
Graphics Press.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ER Tufte (1990) Envisioning information. Graphics Press.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ER Tufte (1997) Visual explanations. Graphics Press.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;WS Cleveland (1993) Visualizing data. Hobart Press.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;WS Cleveland (1994) The elements of graphing data. CRC Press.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A Gelman, C Pasarica, R Dodhia (2002) Let’s practice what we preach:
Turning tables into graphs. The American Statistician 56:121-130.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;NB Robbins (2004) Creating more effective graphs. Wiley.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A Cairo (2013) The functional art: An introduction to information graphics and visualization. New Riders.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;N Yau (2013) Data points: Visualization that means something. Wiley.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also do not cover interactive graphics, a topic that is both too advanced for this course and too unweildy. Some useful resources for those interested in learning more can be found below, and you are encouraged to draw inspiration from those websites in your projects:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://shiny.rstudio.com/&#34;&gt;https://shiny.rstudio.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://d3js.org/&#34;&gt;https://d3js.org/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;code&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Code&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See the link below for the example code; code will be pasted &lt;strong&gt;after&lt;/strong&gt; class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://graphics.wsj.com/infectious-diseases-and-vaccines/?mc_cid=711ddeb86e&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;http://graphics.wsj.com/infectious-diseases-and-vaccines/?mc_cid=711ddeb86e&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://graphics8.nytimes.com/images/2011/02/19/nyregion/19schoolsch/19schoolsch-popup.gif&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;http://graphics8.nytimes.com/images/2011/02/19/nyregion/19schoolsch/19schoolsch-popup.gif&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn3&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/2011/02/19/nyregion/19schools.html&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://www.nytimes.com/2011/02/19/nyregion/19schools.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn4&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Tukey&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Tukey&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn5&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ted.com/talks/hans_rosling_reveals_new_insights_on_poverty?language=en&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://www.ted.com/talks/hans_rosling_reveals_new_insights_on_poverty?language=en&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn6&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ted.com/talks/hans_rosling_shows_the_best_stats_you_ve_ever_seen&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://www.ted.com/talks/hans_rosling_shows_the_best_stats_you_ve_ever_seen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
